Hello and welcome to ANA Academy, a
one-stop destination for the English
medium civil services aspirants. A very
good morning and welcome to the most
detailed Hindu analysis on YouTube.
So let's begin our discussion by first
looking at the topics that we are going
to discuss from the Delhi edition of the
Hindu. I have chosen a total of eight
articles for a detailed analysis.
So let's cover them one by one so that
you don't have to go back and read the
newspaper again. If you guys are liking
our initiatives, do support us by liking
the video and do subscribe to our
channel. Now before we start the
discussion, I have a very very important
announcement. ANAC Academy is presenting
the UNA Academy UPSC summit which will
be conducted on the 5th and 6th of July
that is today and tomorrow on the UNA
Academy app. This gives you an
opportunity to take live sessions from
your top educators and as well as from
bureaucrats, retired diplomats and as
well as from senior military officers
and from toppers to learn about the
strategy that is needed to crack the
elite civil services examination.
You can take a look at the list of
esteemed speakers who will be conducting
special classes and sessions mainly
focused on inspiring the candidates,
motivating the candidates and giving the
right strategy and inputs to help you
crack the IAS exam. So those interested,
please register using the link provided
in the description and attend all these
live special classes on the academy
platform on the 5th and 6th of July.
And if you want the PDF of the Hindu
analysis, please join my telegram
channel by scanning the QR code. After
the session ends, I'll be sharing the
PDF over here. So let's get started and
look at the first article. Let's look at
this important column from page number
six. This column written by Sanjay
Hegay, a senior Supreme Court advocate,
focuses on the democratic backsliding
which we are witnessing in the United
States.
I'm sure all of you are aware that just
yesterday the US marked its independence
day on the 4th of July. The US gained
independence from colonial rule back in
1776.
And since then, the US has been a
cherished democracy, a country which
cherishes its fundamental rights,
liberty, and free speech and expression.
If you look at the Declaration of
Independence, which was drafted by the
founding fathers of the US, it cherishes
democratic values and principles. If you
look at the bill of rights and the
fundamental rights guaranteed in the
American constitution,
it is very clear that United States has
been the bullwark of democracy and a
guiding example for democracies around
the world. But today there are some
disturbing developments happening in the
US. And the writer draws a parallel with
the emergency of 1975 which was seen in
India
which marked
a democratic blot which was a a dark
chapter in Indian democracy and the
writer sees number of parallels between
the developments that are happening in
the US currently and the developments
that preceded the 1975 emergency in
India. So I feel the topic is very very
important for GS paper 2 poly very
relevant for even ethics under GS paper
4 with regard to the topic of
constitutional morality and in fact some
of the arguments are so beautiful in
this article that it could help you in a
essay as well. You can possibly expect a
essay topic related to this. So let's
dive deep into this article. We will go
beyond the article of course and
understand this topic in complete
detail. So first what is the context?
Let's understand the relevance of this
article. As I said the writer is
referring to India's emergency from 1975
to77 under then Prime Minister Indra
Gandhi which marks a dark chapter in
India's democratic history. The writer
points out how easy it is for a
democracy to slide into authoritarian
regime. Most of us we take our free
speech and rights and liberty for
granted.
Citizens generally tend to become
complicent over a period of time.
Institutions get compromised over a
period of time leading to democratic
backsliding. All it takes is one crazy
individual, one authoritarian leader to
wipe out the gains of decades and
centuries of struggle.
It is this important lesson that this
article teaches us.
The writer is presenting the case of two
democracies and the echos of tyranny,
drawing lessons from the 1975 emergency
in India and how this applies to the
rest of the world and why it is
important for citizens and the
institutions in a democratic setup to
stand up and hold the executive
accountable.
Why it is important to defend democracy
day in and day out.
Democracy can't be guaranteed just by a
written constitution or by written laws.
The laws in the constitution can be
subverted. The institutions can be
compromised and in fact the very same
laws and constitution can be misused to
enable the rise of a tyranny to enable
the rise of authoritarian regime.
It is this stark warning that the writer
is giving not just to the US but to the
entire world including India.
We need to draw lessons from history.
And that is exactly what the writer is
uh trying to stress upon. The constant
fight between democracy and tyranny. The
writer says never take democracy for
granted. Democracy is something that
should be preserved and protected from
generation to generation.
If the citizenry becomes complicent, if
institutions are compromised, that is
when you will see a slow erosion of
democracy and the parallel rise of
tyranny and authoritarianism.
So this has a lot of contemporary
significance.
Don't think the topic is not relevant
for the exam. topic is extremely
relevant given the developments that are
happening around the world where we are
seeing a democratic backsliding a
erosion of democratic values and
principles including in one of the
strongest democracies known which is the
United States
in fact this could even be a possible
essay topic as I pointed out the writer
presents a very beautiful statement
which can be directly lifted and given
as a essay topic in the mains exam in
the article the writer writes tyranny
thrives when institutions become hollow.
So this statement has a deeper meaning.
It has deeper implications for a
democratic polity.
How authoritarianism can rise when
democratic institutions become hollow
from the inside.
The writer argues that the threat for a
democracy is not from the outside. It's
not from some outside power, from
external threats. It's primarily
internal. When institutions are subdued
and subverted and the laws and the
constitution itself is misused to enable
the rise of autocratic regime.
It is this internal threat that citizens
have to guard against. Citizens have to
stand up against any such backsliding
that they witness in democratic values
and principles. And we need to draw
lessons from what happened in 1975 in
India and apply this to the rest of the
world.
The writer argues that democracy is as
strong as its institutions and its
people which is again a very strong and
powerful argument and a very correct
argument as well.
You can't assume that liberty will exist
forever. You can't assume that your
fundamental rights are guaranteed
forever. There might be a written
constitution. There might be laws in
place but eventually as Dr. Dr. Ambedkar
also pointed out it all boils down to
the essential goodness of people, the
goodness of leaders to follow the
constitution and the law of the land.
What if
there are elements who come up, rise up
in power, who don't respect the
constitution and the laws, who seek to
undermine them, who use the existing
constitution and laws to subvert the
institutions and erase democracy step by
step in an incremental manner.
See many people they have a very wrong
assumption. There is a myth that rise of
tyranny, rise of authoritarianism
happens through violence and chaos and
it is expected to be a sudden overnight
development.
That is something you see maybe in
countries uh in Africa or in even in
West Asia. But generally we have seen
trends where democracy has been crushed
and authoritarian regimes have risen in
a very gradual incremental manner
step-by-step manner. Sometimes in a
peaceful manner as well they even
legalize the rise of tyranny by
subverting the laws in the constitution.
Essentially they make it legal. This
reminds us of what happened in Germany
in 1930s.
The rise of the Nazi party and Adolf
Hitler
was essentially enabled through
democratic processes through the laws of
the land through elections through the
constitution. Nothing was illegal per
se. If you go strictly by the laws, the
rise of Nazi regime and the rise of
Hitler was perfectly legal and even
democratic in some ways. But you all
know what happened next. It is this
creeping rise of authoritarianism that
one should guard against in democracies
like US and as well as in India.
The writer points out that tyranny can
emerge through legal channels itself. It
might appear to be legal.
It may not be a violent coup. It may not
be engineered through a military capture
of a power or it may not be through a
civil war. It might be done by a elected
government.
by misusing the laws and the
constitutional provisions and that is
exactly what Prime Minister Indra Gandhi
did in 1975
by capturing institutions one by one by
eroding the independence of key
institutions like the judiciary the
parliament
and eventually by threatening the media
by silencing the media which is a key
pillar of a democracy and even before
the citizenry can realize what has
happened they would already be living
under a authoritarian rule.
So history according to the writer may
not repeat itself exactly as it happened
before but definitely it sends out
echoes of the past and if you don't
listen to these echoes of the past if
you don't pay attention to it that is
when democratic countries are going to
pay a price. So to prevent the rise of
tyranny it is very very critical for the
people of the country and the
institutions the democratic institutions
which are vested with the responsibility
to protect democracy to stand up and
hold the government and the regime
accountable.
Now this is where we need to look at
1975 India what happened in the days
preceding the emergency and what
happened during the emergency. how this
was essentially a legal tyranny, a
lawful constitutional tyranny enabled by
our own constitution, enabled by our own
laws.
When Prime Minister Indra Gandhi
suffered
a legal defeat, Allahabad High Court
ruled against the Prime Minister where a
case was being heard alleging that she
had won through electoral fraud which
would essentially lead to the prime
minister resigning and stepping down.
This marked the trigger for the rise of
authoritarian tendency under then Prime
Minister Indra Gandhi.
By then Indra Gandhi had essentially
established the the cult of popularity.
She was seen as a very popular leader
amongst the masses. And the influence of
Indra Gandhi was so prevalent across
institutions that even the judiciary,
even the media and eventually the
opposition, they all crumbled under the
weight of a authoritarian leader.
In fact, if you look at the records and
the historical writings of that period,
it is reported that Indra Gandhi even
tried to enroll the support of the
military, reached out to the then Indian
army chief who denied to play a role in
politics and established the
professional neutrality, the political
neutrality of the armed forces.
But if you look at how the judiciary
crumbled, the Supreme Court in the ADM
Jabalpur case delivered a horrific
judgment. The Supreme Court in a
majority verdict ruled that right to
life under article 21 which is often
considered as sacrosan.
The Supreme Court ruled in the ADM
Jabalpur case that right to life can be
suspended which means the state has the
right to take your life
even by not following the established
procedure under law.
There was only one judge in this
particular case who desented that was
justice HR Kana became a legend later on
as he managed to bring up the courage to
stand up against authoritarianism and
the violation of rights that was taking
place when the entire judiciary had
collapsed and judges were essentially
pledging loyalty to the prime minister
was building up a personality cult. It
was justice HR kana who stood up against
this judgment dissented and eventually
justice HR kana was even targeted for
this judgment. He would never get the
opportunity to become the chief justice
of India.
But if you look at how the media was
essentially curbed,
the freedom of press was snatched. How
civil society was crushed, the
opposition was crushed by the Indra
Gandhi regime. Right? that that is
something which is which is unexpected
in a democracy. Nobody expects that to
happen. But through the law of the land
through the constitutional provisions
itself by declaring a national emergency
under article 352
under article 352 the prime minister
assumed complete totalitarian control.
Lacks of citizens were jailed.
Opposition leaders journalists were
thrown in jail, incarcerated.
Free speech and free press was curbed.
The police, the bureaucracy, they all
crumbled.
The bureaucracy was more interested in
pledging loyalty to the prime minister
instead of standing up against the
democratic erosion. Now these are the
institutions that the writer is talking
about. The judiciary, the parliament,
the bureaucracy itself, the security
forces and the police. They all
eventually crumbled
and dissent basically became treason.
Descent which is a a guaranteed
fundamental right, a core tenate of a
democracy became treason became an
antiational activity.
Power became personal where power was
cornered by one leader and wielded by
the unelected as well.
The writer talks about the excesses that
were committed by Indra Gandhi's uh son
Sanjay Gandhi which would lead to large
scale atrocities.
How opposition leaders would be
targeted. How the media would be
targeted as well. Torture would be
enabled in in custody. The police became
subservient to the wishes of the
authoritarian regime.
Rights essentially became privileges.
Of course, what what else will happen if
the Supreme Court itself is declaring
that article 21 can be suspended when
article 352 has been invoked that is
when a national emergency is in place.
Supreme Court basically said in the ADM
Jabur case that right to life is not
guaranteed anymore.
So this was the alarming descent of
India into authoritarianism.
But fortunately once emergency was
lifted and elections were held the
Indian electorate which had woken up to
the threat which had woken up from its
slumber picked out that regime in the
coming elections and that is how India
managed to build back a stronger
democracy.
But of course the threat remains even
today
threat remains not just in India but in
any democratic country this could happen
again.
That is the reason why the writer
strongly opposes the rise of cult
personality.
The writer opposes hero worship.
The writer is advising the readers to
never worship the leaders. Don't put
them on a pedestal.
Hold your leaders accountable. Hold the
regime accountable. That is the job, the
task of every citizen. That is the task
of every institution as well.
The writer firmly rejects blind loyalty.
The writer rejects cult and hero
worship. If you study what happened in
Vimma Germany, the rise of Nazi party
and Hitler's rise to power, that is
exactly what happened as well. So the
writer is drawing parallels with the
current developments, the disturbing
developments under Donald Trump in the
US. The writer indicates how Donald
Trump can subdue all the institutions
and legally constitutionally establish
authoritarian regime in the US much like
how Indra Gandhi did in 1975 in India.
This is where the concept of
constitutional morality comes up. The
role of democratic institutions come up.
This reminds me of
the stand taken by Hi Kamat, a freedom
fighter and a member of the constituent
assembly. He raised a stark warning in
the constituent assembly debates when
the emergency provisions were being
debated.
He took a firm stand against article
352.
He said this is extraordinary power
which is being vested with the
democratic government. Essentially,
you're putting faith in the goodness of
a leader, in the goodness of a regime,
hoping that democracy would be
protected.
But what if there is a authoritarian
leader who comes up, they can misuse
these provisions? In fact, HV Kamat
compared article 352 with emergency
provisions that were available in the
constitution of whimar Germany, which
Hitler would essentially utilize. to
enable the legal constitutional rise of
a dictatorship.
So, HV Kamat was proven right in 1975
that institutions can be easily
subverted and this can be done legally.
None of it would be illegal. It would
all be according to the law, according
to the constitution and this can become
a weapon in the hands of authoritarian
regimes.
That was a stark warning given by HV Kat
about the disturbing emergency
provisions, the lack of checks and
balances in them and how easily it could
be hijacked by a authoritarian leader.
So that's why the writer is very clear
that please get rid of this myth this
assumption that you have that
authoritarian regimes are always violent
that the rise of tyranny is always uh
through chaos that may not be the case
can happen legally legitimately. It can
be done by subverting the constitution
misusing the constitutional principles
and more importantly by eroding the
institutions by hollowing out the
institutions.
If judiciary can be threatened, if the
opposition can be controlled, if the
media can be subverted, that marks the
death of democracy. And parallelly, if
there is the rise of a cult personality,
right? You have all the ingredients to
establish authoritarian regime even
before the citizens can realize what has
happened, even before citizens can
realize that their rights have been
snatched away.
This is the deep concern that is coming
up in the United States. a clear
democratic erosion. The writer correctly
points out that Donald Trump's erratic
policies,
right? There might be a larger
disturbing uh intention behind it. Right
now, if you look at the key democratic
institutions in the US, more or less
they have been compromised. The in the
US Congress, both in the Senate and in
the House of Representatives, Trump has
a clear majority. In the Supreme Court
as well, majority of the judges are
appointees of Donald Trump, loyal to the
leader and the Republican party. The
media, at least the traditional media,
is being subverted in the US
with a disturbing rise of so-called
social media, the new media influencers
who are more than willing to be loyal to
the regime and the leader. You have
witnessed the rise of cult personality,
the usage of existing laws and
constitutional provisions to subvert
basic rights in the country.
The way in which
migrants have been targeted. The way in
which department of justice in the US
has been weaponized clearly points to a
democratic erosion that's happening
within. It's like a informal emergency
which has already been brought in where
the executive has assumed almost
totalitarian control through legal
constitutional methods.
So the US is basically just a few steps
away from witnessing what happened in
India in 1975.
That is where the role of citizens
becomes equally important as important
as the role of institutions.
The writer is urging the citizens to
demand accountability from the
leadership.
That's why you should never fall victim
to the sheep mentality, the herd
mentality where you blindly follow a
party or a leader, fall under cult
worship. Instead, you should always be
vigilant. You should always exercise
your democratic rights, your right to
vote, your right to protest, your right
to seek information. These are the
checks and balances in a democracy that
can protect your liberty.
Similarly, the institutions have to
perform their role. The media should
remain vigilant and independent. The
judiciary should maintain the separation
with the executive and the legislature
and should be the ultimate guardian of
the spirit of the constitution. The
judiciary should not merely interpret
the laws but it should protect the laws
and the constitution and the very spirit
and the ethos of a democ democratic
society.
Similarly, the legislature, the
bureaucracy,
right, the whole government machinery
has a responsibility.
If they see such authoritarian
tendencies, instead of pledging loyalty,
they should stand up and rebel and stand
with the citizens to prevent the
democratic backsliding and erosion.
This statement I feel is very very
important which you can directly use in
your answers. Democracy must be
reclaimed by every generation.
Because over a period of time citizenry
becomes complicit.
Now you look at India. India had a
difficult struggle against colonial
regime. We won our freedom through great
difficulty through great sacrifices of
our freedom fighters.
But after instilling democracy in the
country and and the democratic values
over the decades citizens have become
complicent. They have taken democracy
for granted. Right? We all have taken
liberty for granted. This complicency is
what can be exploited by authoritarian
leaders. That's why the writer says that
every generation should be instilled
with the value of protecting democracy.
You have to constantly involve yourself
in democratic activism.
And this could include the mere act of
questioning the government, questioning
the leadership, protesting against
unfair rules and laws and policies.
And that is how democracy can be
protected by every subsequent
generation. Every generation needs an
experience in reclaiming democracy.
Democracy is not something that will
always exist.
Democracy will erode if it is not
reclaimed and protected constantly. So I
feel this is a very powerful statement
the writer is making. See fortunately in
the people of India woke up to the
threat. They realized what happened
during the emergency period of 2 years.
They voted out the government and
restored democracy and further checks
and balances were created for example
through the 44th 44th constitutional
amendment act to prevent the blatant
misuse of article 352. But if the
institutions and the people don't remain
vigilant, such developments could easily
be repeated in any country. And that is
the stark warning that the writer is
giving out. If we don't defend
democracy, if we assume that someone
else will do it, right? This is what
happens when you're complicent, even
though you know what is happening,
right? Even though you know that there
is a clear erosion of democracy that's
taking place, right? Be it in any
country, there is assumption amongst the
people that someone else will stop it
from happening, right? They'll put blind
faith in the judiciary, in the media, in
the opposition, in the constitution or
they'll expect the civil society when
they don't realize that they themselves
are part of the civil society. Democracy
is something that should be actively
defended by each and every citizen. That
is when the institutions will also stand
up because see eventually what are
institutions? Institutions are also made
up by people.
Those who hold these key positions of
power, especially those who hold key
constitutional offices, they have a
bigger responsibility to protect
democratic ethos and hold the government
uh under check and keep it accountable.
This reminds me of a popular statement
by Thomas Payne. Let the law be the
king,
not men or not mobs, not some president
or not some prime minister. Let the law
be the king. If you don't believe in
this principle, if you don't stand up
for for these values, you will see a
erosion. You will see the decline into
authoritarianism, a return to monarchy.
You might remember Trump even posted
through his official social media
accounts crowning himself as the king of
United States.
Though it was meant to be a meme or a
joke, one wouldn't be surprised if Trump
was not kidding. And that is the warning
the writer brings to us through this
important article. Now please take up
this mains question based on what we
have discussed. But in this question
I'll help you by discussing a model
answer. I'll give you the approach that
you can follow with the specific points
mentioned. But I expect all of you to
make use of this discussion to write an
answer and practice your answer writing.
So what you can do is if you read the
question right the question is mainly
focused on how democracies can be
subverted not just through coups or
violence but through legal and
institutional capture. So that is a
statement which has been given the
context is in the context of 1975
emergency of India and how it has global
lessons
why constitutional morality
institutional vigilance is important in
a democracy that is the focus of the
question. So once you understand the
demand of the question, you can start
your answer by defining democratic
erosion. What constitutes democratic
erosion? Maybe give some examples
how judiciary can be subverted, how the
media can be controlled. Give some
examples maybe by taking precedents from
India's experience with emergency or any
global example. Mention how laws are
used
to curtail liberty. how in a legal
constitutional manner your rights can be
curbed, your liberty can be taken away.
So you're clearly illustrating that rise
of tyranny may not just be through
dictatorial route or through violence
and coups. It can happen legally,
constitutionally as well and maybe even
use a quote to enhance your argument.
Then in the body you have to provide
specific details. You can break down the
answer into how legal mechanisms are
misused. Give some specific details
here. talk about the suspension of
fundamental rights that was done under
powers of article 352 by imposing a
national emergency in 1975
by using the excuse of internal
disturbance.
It was this provision of article 352
that was misused by Indra Gandhi which
was later removed through the 44th
constitutional amendment act. mention
laws like the MISAs maintenance of
internal security act which was used by
the Indra Gandhi regime to detain all
the dissenters and the opposition and
throw them in jails. This was legally
done. It was lawful.
Mention the ADM Jabalpur case. How the
Supreme Court itself was undermining one
of the core fundamental rights right to
life.
The role of institutions in democratic
decline. talk about how judiciary,
bureaucracy, media can be subverted.
Maybe give an example as to what's
happening in the US. Then bring up a
discussion on constitutional morality.
Here you can refer to the warnings given
by HV Kat, the role of citizens
in protecting the constitution and
liberty and elaborate the role of
citizens in the civil society. Why
public resistance is important. how
citizens are the guardians of the
constitution and the liberty which is
guaranteed in a democratic setup and
finally provide some contemporary
relevance focus on what's happening in
US or similar developments in other
countries and highlight how personality
cult and control over other organs of
the state could lead to subversion of
democracy and the rise of tyranny and
finally conclude your answer by
reiterating the core idea The democracy
needs to be reclaimed by every
generation that citizens and
institutions are the final guardians of
a democratic setup. You can even use the
quote of Thomas Spain, right? And point
out democracy is not something which you
can take for granted. You can't be
complicent about your liberty. something
which has to be constantly protected and
for that you need a vigilant citizenry
and you need a independent uh setup of
institutions to protect the liberty that
is guaranteed in a democratic setup. So
this can be a good conclusion. So I hope
you use the answer writing approach I've
given to write and practice answers. Now
let's look at another important article.
Prime Minister Narendra Modi has visited
a Caribbean nation Trinidad and Tobago.
You might know that the prime minister
is on
a visit to multiple countries, right?
The prime minister visited Ghana in
Africa. Now he's in the Caribbean. He'll
be visiting Argentina as well, Brazil
for the brick summit. So almost five
countries are being covered by the prime
minister in this uh back-to-back visits.
And in Trinidad and Tobago, the prime
minister has focused on the role of the
Indian diaspora.
He has paid tribute to the Indian
community abroad. He has hailed the
contribution of 35 million strong Indian
diaspora which is distributed around the
world. Now the point is why did the PM
do this in Trinidad and Tobago? That's
because this Caribbean country is
primarily made up of people of Indian
origin.
180 years ago, batches of Indians were
transported to these faraway islands by
the British under the exploitative,
brutal, indentured labor system. Today,
a large part of the Caribbean region is
inhabited by the descendants of the
Indian community, the Indian laborers
who were transported and exploited by
the British. And does across the
Caribbean you see a very strong Indian
cultural influence and presence.
If you look at the West Indies cricket
team, right? If you look at the names of
West Indian cricketers like Shivar and
Chandraal and others, you you might have
wondered how come in such a far away
country people have uh Hindu sounding
names, Indian sounding names. Then if
you're familiar with Caribbean culture,
the food, the music, uh even the
religion which is followed, right? It's
quite similar to what you see back home
in India. So if you ever wondered what
is that connection because Indians were
transported long ago 180 years ago and
today across the Caribbean especially in
Jamaica in Trinidad and Tobago even in
some South American countries as well in
the Latin America region you find a very
very strong Indian community. So the
prime minister has interacted with the
Indian community here, announced few new
initiatives to take forward India's
close relations with the Indian
community across the Caribbean.
So before we talk about this, let's
understand the role of the Indian
diaspora, the presence and distribution
of the Indian diaspora. Let's even talk
about the indentured labor system
because the prime minister has brought
up a mention of all these points during
his address to the people of Trinidad
and Tobago.
Now first where is Trinidad and Tobago
located? This can be a places in news
question a map based question in
prelims. It's part of the Caribbean
region which is often referred to
colloquially as the West Indies. It's
very close to South America located just
off the shore of Venezuela.
Right? You here you can see North
America, the United States, the Florida
region, right? You can see Central
America over here, the Panama Canel and
this would be South America. So in the
Caribbean Sea, you have these islands
that are spread out, often referred to
as the Caribbean islands.
So Trinet and Tobago is one of the major
Caribbean nations, a sovereign country
of its own. You also have Jamaica, St.
Kits and Nevice, Barbados and many
others. And there are also other
countries here such as Cuba, Haiti,
Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico and the
others.
So in this region Trinidad and Tobago
has one of the highest members of Indian
community amongst its population. The
country is located just off the coast of
Venezuela very close to Guyana as well.
Right in the same region you can see
Surinam and French Guyana. Now across
all these countries you find a strong
Indian community. Even today,
even in Guyana, which was under the
British, Indian laborers were
transported to this country as well in
large numbers. You might remember last
year, just last year, Prime Minister
Modi visited Guyana, met with the Indian
community. Even in Surina,
there's a very strong Indian diaspora.
The descendants of Indian laborers, they
form a strong connect with India. Even
today in French Guyana as well, you find
a strong Indian diaspora. many of them
still follow uh Indian culture, Indian
practices etc. Then across the Caribbean
region apart from Trinidad and Tobago,
you also have Jamaica as I said, St.
Kits and Nevis, Barbados and others. And
the Indian community has even spread to
other nearby countries like Dominican
Republic, even parts of Cuba and Haiti
and Puerto Rico and others. So there's a
very very strong presence of the Indian
community here and it's all because of
the indentured labor system of the
British.
See in 1800s
Britain had of course become the
predominant global power with colonies
around the world from the Pacific to the
Atlantic.
So these British colonies and British
enterprises such as East India Company,
they were essentially dependent on
African slaves
to run and manage the colonial
businesses and enterprises.
Africans were brutally exploited under
the slavery system. They were not even
treated like humans. They were treated
like products or commodities to be
captured and traded in these slave
markets.
For example, in the infamous slave
market of Zanzibar in Africa where
British
royalty, the British royalty, the
British enterprises, they would buy and
sell African slaves and exploit them
across their colonies and essentially
deny them basic human rights. But
eventually the abuse of African slaves
led to an awakening in Britain and
eventually the British Parliament in
abolished slavery.
The British Parliament after centuries
of abuse of Africans finally adopted a
law prohibiting slavery. Slavery
abolition act was passed with the
British Parliament in 1833. So all of a
sudden British enterprises and the
British royalty. They lost their labor
force.
Right? They would never pay the African
slaves. They would treat them as they as
if they own them. Right? They would be
owners of these African slaves. They
would treat them like commodities. They
would treat them as subhumans and
exploit and violate their human rights
at will. Now they could no longer do
this freely as they used to do before.
Now all of a sudden there was a need for
cheap labor,
a need to replace the African slaves
and the British came out with yet
another exploitative system which is the
indentured labor system also known as
the Germita system
and this time the target would be
Indians.
They essentially replaced African slaves
with Indians and continued slavery or at
least some sort of bonded exploitative
labor in a different form.
They would trick and deceive and dupe
Indians to sign these labor contracts
promising lucrative jobs in foreign
lands. In some cases, they would force
and threaten and forcibly transfer
Indians and their entire families to
faraway colonies, especially those who
were in jails, those who were not paying
taxes. They would be rounded up by the
British and they would be transported
away these to these far away islands. In
many cases they would be deceived and
tricked with the job of with with the
offer of a lucrative job. These
contracts would be like for three five
years. They would promise them to bring
them back and pay them good salaries as
well. But once they would transport to
them to these far away islands, they
would dump them over there, mistreat
them, abuse them, they wouldn't pay
their salaries, they wouldn't give them
good living conditions and they had no
opportunity to return back ever.
So under the Germita system, the
indentured labor system, the first batch
of Indian laborers were transported in
1834, just one year after slavery,
African slavery was abolished. Now can
you tell me to which country were the
first batch of Indian laborers
transported by the British under the
indentured labor system? Please mention
this in the comments below. Let's see if
you can answer this question.
So around the world British colonies
were flooded by Indian laborers
primarily from the
region of today's Bihar, Uttar Pradesh
and Jarkand and as well as from the
Madras presidency as well and from
different nukes and corners of India but
primarily the Indians who were
transported lacks and lacks of Indian
families majority of them came from the
Hindi heartland the Bjpuri heartland of
Bihar uh the Aad region of UP and parts
of today's jar. This was the region
which primarily contributed to
indentured laborers then as well as from
other regions as well from Bengal from
northwest uh frontier province from
Madras presidency Bombay presidency as
well right a lot of Indians were
transported with their families and
dumped on these British colonies that
they controlled. So from Fiji in the
Pacific
to South Africa and across
East Africa in countries like Kenya,
Tanzania and the others in countries
like Mauritius in the Indian Ocean and
also in far away countries as you saw on
the map in South America in the
Caribbean from these Caribbean islands
to South American countries that you
have today such as Trinidad, Tobago then
you have uh Guyana, Surinam across all
these British colonies, Indians were
transported and dumped and the
descendants of these Indian families are
essentially the Indian diaspora today,
the Indian community that maintains a
close connection with India. Just look
at this map which depicts the movement
and the forceful transportation of
Indian laborers during the period of
1830s to early 1900s. For nearly a
century, the British, they blatantly
transported Indians, many times tricking
them, deceiving them or forcing them.
They even pushed Indian laborers to Sri
Lanka, Moritius across Southeast Asia,
particularly for tea plantations in the
Malaysia region.
They needed cheap labor to maintain
these British enterprises.
In Maicius, their focus was on sugar
cultivation.
Same with Fiji and across the Caribbean
South America region as well. Their main
focus was to find cheap labor to run the
sugar plantations and the factories use
them as cheap exploitative labor for
construction and other projects across
Africa. So around the world lacks of
Indian families were transported and
that is the reason why one of the prime
reasons why today India has a very well
spread out and distributed diaspora.
So this map which is slightly old tells
you that the Indian diaspora community
is 26 million strong but this data is
slightly old as I told you but the map
is relevant. Today the strength of the
Indian diaspora is around 35 million as
prime minister Modi has pointed out
yesterday
which means 3.5 crore people around the
world
some of them are still Indian citizens
are NRIs but many of them would be
people of Indian origin. So it's a mix
of NRIs and the PIOS
and India sees them with great respect.
India sees them as valuable assets in
diplomacy. So from North America to
South America to Africa to uh the
Pacific
across the Asia region right in every
nukan corner of the world. Today India
has a very very strong diaspora
presence. Of course in modern times
Indians have moved out. They migrated
primarily for better educational and uh
employment opportunities. Many of them
even enter countries illegally today and
eventually it gives India the strength
cultural soft power influence with a
very very strong diaspora community and
probably the Chinese diaspora is quite
larger than Indian diaspora but India is
all set to overtake China as well in
terms of its strength of diaspora around
the world. Now why are we talking so
much about the Indian diaspora? Why did
the prime minister specifically mention
this in Trinidad and Tobago? Because the
Indian diaspora plays a critical role in
our foreign policy. And that's what you
need to understand. As the prime
minister has pointed out, each member of
the Indian community abroad, whether
they are Indian citizens or people of
Indian origin, they act as the Raj
Dutas. Essentially they act as the
ambassadors of India, the cultural
ambassadors of India
since they practice Indian culture in
their day-to-day life, right? They could
be Hindus, Muslims, Buddhists, Janss,
Sikhs, eventually they're all rooted in
their Indianness connected to the Indian
civilization and India's cultural ethos.
They celebrate Indian festivals. They
cook Indian food.
They essentially promote India's
cultural influence and soft power
influence on a day-to-day basis creating
a unique leverage for Indian diplomacy.
Even without the government of India
doing anything, India will automatically
enjoy an amount of goodwill and trust in
foreign countries because of the
cultural soft power influence created by
the Indian diaspora community.
Now this is a incredible power in
diplomacy. Apart from acting as cultural
ambassadors,
they might rise up to positions of power
giving us leverage with foreign
governments.
The Indian community might constitute a
key electorate.
They might become a key vote bank in
certain countries. So we have seen for
example countries like let's say Canada,
US uh UK as well where Indian electorate
uh play a critical role in the elections
and in the formation of the government
where political parties and leaders try
to appease the Indian community
and we have seen Indians rising up
either in business or in politics or
within the government rising up to
senior positions even becoming head of
states and head of governments.
So that gives India a very unique
leverage in foreign countries, the
ability to even influence foreign
governments and their policy if
necessary which could favor India and
its interests.
And more importantly, the Indian
community could send remittances back
home.
Money that they are earning, they might
send it back to their families back home
in India. And today did you know India
is the world's largest recipient of
inbound remittances
and this is critical for the Indian
economy. Today India is receiving
consistently more than hundred billion
dollars in the last 3 years. We have
recently overtaken China as well when it
comes to inbound remittances. Until
2021, China was the world's largest
recipient of remittances in general. But
India has clearly overtaken China as
well in the last few years. And in the
last 3 years in particular, we are
receiving consistently more than hundred
billion. And this foreign exchange that
we receive is crucial to bridge our
current account deficit
adds to India's forex reserves and helps
in bridging the current account deficit
and thus stabilizes the macroeconomic
conditions in the Indian economy. You
can also see which are the top
contributing countries for inward
remittances into India.
Clearly United States comes out at the
top. The Gulf region is a major
contributor led by United Arab Emirates,
UK, Singapore and many other countries.
So the Indian community not only acts as
cultural ambassadors and uh give give us
the ability to influence foreign
governments and foreign politics but
they send inward remittances to India
which is critical for the Indian
economy. So it's only natural for the
Indian government to look after the
Indian community to ensure their safety,
their well-being. That explains why
India rushes to evacuate the Indian
community when there is a crisis in a
foreign country. Let's say a war breaks
out or a disaster strikes a country. We
immediately launch evacuation missions.
You saw that recently as well during the
crisis in West Asia or the crisis in
Ukraine or crisis in Afghanistan.
India also prioritizes the well-being of
the Indian community. Looking after
their interests, looking after their uh
well-being, protecting their economic
rights, providing them legal assistance,
providing them consular uh and visa
assistance.
So the prime minister has announced few
initiatives in Trinidad and Tobago while
paying tribute to the 35 million strong
Indian community abroad. The prime
minister has announced that India is
setting up a database
for the Girmita community.
India is finally creating
a detailed database of the indentured
laborers and their families. India is
going to document
the exact place
and the ancestral families that left the
country.
and they would be mapped with the
current generation of
people of Indian origin abroad
so that they are able to trace back
their cultural roots.
India will be setting up this database
of indentured laborers to try and
identify these ancestral families who
are transported by the British. Locate
them specifically to the place where
they were transported from where they
belong to and connect them with the
country where they have moved where
subsequent generations descendants are
present so that they can trace back
their cultural roots to India.
Then prime minister has also announced
that India is rolling out the UPI
payment interface in Trinidad and
Tobago.
India's UPI has already gone global. In
fact, UPSC has already asked a prelims
question on this in 2025 prelims. India
has already extended UPI payments in
Nepal, Sri Lanka, Singapore, France and
UAE and other countries. Now India's UPI
is being rolled out in the Caribbean in
Trinidad and Tobago where uh especially
on the island of Trinidad you have more
than five lakh people of Indian origin
they would also be provided
with the OCI card a sixth generation
Indian community they would be eligible
for the OCI status overseas citizen of
India where they would enjoy privileges
such as visa-free travel to India and
and better access to the country and
investments in the country as well not
just to visit the country for connecting
with their ancestral roots but also to
find opportunities and invest in the
country. So India would be extending the
OCI facility for sixth generation uh
community members of the Indian
community in Trinidad and Tobago and the
country is also marking the 180th
anniversary of the arrival of Indian
laborers uh in the Caribbean this year
in 2025. So India would be part of these
celebrations as well and again that
tells you why this visit is so important
uh to this Caribbean country. So please
take up this practice question based on
what we have discussed. The indentured
labor system was a continuation of
colonial exploitation in a different
form. Discuss how this system
contributed to the creation and
distribution of the Indian diaspora
across the world. Highlight the
socioeconomic and political roles played
by these diaspora communities in their
host countries. So clearly there are
three different parts to this question.
So I hope all of you will be able to
write a good answer and please post your
answers in the comment section. Now
let's quickly look at the other small
articles in today's paper and wrap up
the discussion. On the front page we
have this article related to
international relations and Indian
economy. India has informed the WTO
that we are going to be levying
reciprocal tariffs on the US.
As you all know, Donald Trump has
unleashed a tariff war against almost
every key trading partner of the US.
Earlier in March this year, the Trump
administration announced around 26%
tariffs on automobile exports from
India.
Two specific automobile exports from
India were targeted by the US government
with higher tariffs on these Indian
exports. So this has hurt the Indian
auto industry especially the MSME sector
which produces most of the components
and spare parts. Now according to India
what the US has done is in violation of
WTO rules and norms.
See under the GAT the general agreement
on tariffs and trade which is at the
core of WTO
and also according to the agreement on
safeguards.
A country when it is levying tariffs
against another country it has to inform
the WTO and hold consultations
before such tariff is levied. This is
mandatory according to WTO provisions.
Under the agreement on safeguard, we
have article 12.3 and article 8 which
clearly specify these obligations on a
country. It helps create a level playing
field. It helps create a fair trading
order so no one country can target the
other unfairly.
So when US levied these tariffs on
India's automobile exports into the US
market, the US neither informed the WTO
nor it held consultations with India.
Through consultations, you can overcome
any distrust or any concerns and you can
arrive at a a mid ground. But the US
never bothered to follow the agreement
on safeguards. It didn't even inform the
WTO and it never held consultations with
India regarding the tariffs on
automotive export from India.
They have just levied these tariffs
which has started started hurting the
Indian automobile industry. So under the
WTO rules now India reserves the right
to invoke the powers of safeguards and
protect our own industry by levying
counter tariffs by levying reciprocal
tariffs.
So according to India's assessment,
India suffered a revenue loss of up to
$724 million
because of the American tariffs. So now
India has chosen to American exports to
India and we are levying counter tariffs
to recover this lost amount.
Almost exactly $724 million is likely to
be recovered by India by placing higher
tariffs on certain American exports to
India. Now this is what you mean by
reciprocal tariffs. Now this tit fortat
measure could derail the ongoing trade
talks between India and US.
The Trump administration has already
threatened India with 27% tariffs across
the board across the spectrum to target
Indian exports to the US. India has a
very significant trading relationship
with the US. The bilateral trade volume
is more than hundred billion dollars and
best part is India enjoys a trade
surplus. Meaning the US is a critical
export market for India especially for
our MSME sector, our agriculture sector
as well, even our manufacturing and
services industry. They're heavily
dependent on the American market for
exports. So these tariffs threatened by
Trump administration can completely
derail our exports and significantly
hurt our domestic industries.
As of now, the Trump administration has
paused the tariffs and a 10% flat tariff
is applicable for all the trade
partners. So, India is rushing to
negotiate a mini trade deal
in order to prevent the impact of these
tariff wars that Trump administration
has triggered. Indian officials have
recently visited the US. In fact, India,
US have a deadline that by 9th of July
which is fast approaching. They should
be able to finalize a mini trade deal or
else the higher tariffs will kick into
effect. So India is almost rushing with
the US to finalize a mini trade
agreement. According to reports, we are
at the last stretch of finalizing a mini
trade deal to avoid these deadly tariffs
from the US.
Parallelly, India has countered some of
the tariffs with reciprocal measures and
it appears to be most likely a
deliberate tactic by India, negotiating
tactic to gain leverage over the US.
Since American tariffs have caused a
nominal loss of $724 million for India,
India now is saying that you have
violated the WTO rules. So we will
invoke the safeguard mechanism under WTO
and retaliate with reciprocal tariffs.
This could give India the leverage in
the ongoing trade talks. So this is a
developing story. So let's wait and
watch as to what happens.
Next on page 11, please make a
correction. On page number 11 under the
economy section, we have this article
that refers to the aluminum vision
document and copper vision document
which has been brought out by the
government of India.
See these minerals, metals are very
crucial for any economy, right? Aluminum
is used across various industries from
aerospace to defense uh to construction.
Then if you look at copper, copper is a
critical mineral finding various
applications in electronics industry,
defense and aerospace industry and as
well as in upcoming sectors like
electric vehicles, solar power,
renewable energy and other key emerging
sectors.
So India is gearing up for the upcoming
demand for aluminum, copper and other
key minerals and we are laying out a
road map, a vision is being laid out by
the Indian government. Prime Minister
Modi has set 2047 as the target for
India to become a developed nation to
become a vixit barat.
So as India marches towards this goal,
the demand for some key minerals and
metals is going to increase
significantly. So according to the
aluminum vision document which has been
released by the government of India
recently, India expects
a sixfold jump
in the production
of aluminium by 2047.
See currently India is the second
largest aluminum producer in the world.
Is that clear? India is the second
largest
producer of aluminum in the world. But
however, our global share is very very
small. Though we are the second largest
producer, our global share is just 6% of
the total global production of aluminum.
Now this is something India would like
to correct. India would like to increase
its share of global production of
aluminum in the coming decades. And the
vision document lays out a path for
India to increase aluminum production by
six times by 2047 compared to current
levels. So we are going to do this with
implementation of better technologies,
sustainable mining which focuses on
environment protection as well and also
focusing on recycling.
India will not only scale up mining for
these essential ores but we will also
step up the processing and the
production
by investing in sustainable technology
environment friendly technology so that
with minimal pollution minimal damage to
the environment we can extract and
process and produce these key minerals
and metals while focusing on recycling
as well. So this three-pronged approach
has been laid down under the vision
document. Then if you look at the copper
vision document that has been released,
the government is expecting a six-fold
increase in demand
for copper by 2047
in India's domestic manufacturing
industry within our country where we are
going to witness a six time increase
compared to current levels by 2047 with
regard to the demand for copper. Which
means India will have to scale up the
production. We have to scout for new
resources because India is not really
blessed with copper reserves. We don't
have sufficient copper reserves. We have
to scout for copper copper reserves
around the world. Secure mines
mining and production within the country
and also become self-reliant
given that copper is a critical mineral.
So this is the road map which has been
laid down under the vision document.
These vision documents also talk about
increasing India's boxite production and
uh production of other key minerals as
well by adopting new technologies by
focusing more on recycling and that is
the road map India is drawing for itself
in order to ensure that we have the key
ingredients on raw materials which could
make India a vixit bat by 2047.
Next on page 12, we have a very
important development. Russia has become
the first country in the world to
officially recognize the Taliban regime
in Afghanistan.
Please make a note this is a very very
big development.
The Taliban which toppled the Afghan
civilian government in 2021 and captured
power has established an intim regime.
As you all know, Taliban happens to be
an extremist
insurgent organization
which is often seen as a terrorist
organization as well by few countries.
So the Taliban regime had not been
officially recognized by any country
till now though several countries have
struck deals with Taliban and they
maintain unofficial ties with Taliban.
For example, US struck a deal with
Taliban to exit the country and
eventually paved the way for Taliban to
return to power. China
has maintained ties with Taliban. It has
even allowed Taliban's ambassador to be
stationed in Beijing and China maintains
an official diplomatic ties though China
has not given official recognition.
Please note, China has not given
official recognition to Taliban.
Official diplomatic ties have not been
set up but it maintains very close
relations just one step short of
official diplomatic ties. Same with all
the other major powers be it Iran,
Turkey, European powers, Pakistan,
India.
India if you look at India's position
India had a very complex history with
the Taliban since the Taliban was
largely seen as a puppet of Pakistan's
deep state the ISI and the Pakistani
army because especially when Taliban was
in power for the first time from 96 to
2001 Taliban was seen to be nurturing
and cultivating anti-India terrorist
groups at the behest of Pakistan's ISI
Pakistan was using the Taliban regime
and breeding anti-India terror groups
like Lashkar
Jes Muhammad and the others along the
Afghanistan Pakistan border to target
India. So India had cut off all ties
with the then Taliban regime. Taliban
also had broken all ties with India.
India saw Taliban as a terrorist group
for many years. In fact, we didn't even
engage with Taliban directly until 2021.
But after Taliban came back to power and
this time Taliban is slightly different.
It's been trying to seek recognition and
it's been quoting India's support. India
started reaching out to Taliban and the
Indian ambassador in Qatar
was officially asked to engage with
Taliban regime because Taliban maintains
a political office in Dha the capital of
Qatar. So starting from 2021, India
started its engagement with Taliban, its
official engagement and we have slowly
stepped up our relations. When Taliban
captured power again in 2021, we had cut
off all diplomatic ties. We shut down
our embassy and consulates as well. But
now we have reopened.
We have reopened our diplomatic
missions.
The Indian embassy in Kabul
has been reopened
with a very skeletal minimal presence
and Indian officials have been engaging
with the Taliban leadership. And
recently India's foreign secretary
Vikram Misri met with the foreign
minister of the interim regime of
Taliban in Dubai.
Uh Vikram Mishri met with Mutaki the
foreign affairs minister of the Afghan
interim government. And more importantly
last month in May external affairs
minister Dr. Jai Shankar held a
telephonic conversation
held a phone conversation with Mutaki
the foreign affairs minister of the
Taliban government. Now this marks the
first ever ministerial engagement
between India and Taliban. So we are
maintaining unofficial ties officially.
India has not recognized the Taliban
government.
Right? We have not allowed Taliban to
send uh its ambassador to Delhi.
However, India has allowed Taliban to
appoint console generals in Mumbai and
in its consulates in Hyderabad only to
provide visa and consular services. So,
India is also maintaining that middle
ground that tight balance because on one
hand Taliban is seen as a extremist
group which is seen to violate gender
rights and minority rights and crush
human rights. So you can't see be seen
to be engaging with such a regime and
also factions of Taliban like Hakani
network right leaders of Hakkari network
are also in power currently the interior
minister of Taliban Sirajuin Hakani is a
globally wanted terrorist his faction
Hakani network has been involved in
terror attacks against India targeting
Indian diplomats Indian officers and
workers in Afghanistan
right Hakani network has been
responsible for bombing the Indian
embassy and consulates and Indian
projects in Afghanistan but despite that
India has been engaging with Taliban
unofficially without giving official
recognition. So Russia has now moved to
provide the first official recognition
and this is a very very big development.
And what is ironic is that
the predecessor of Russia, the Soviet
Union treated the Afghan mujahjahide
which is the predecessor of the Taliban
as an existential threat. In fact, the
USSR invaded Afghanistan in 1979
primarily to counter the radical forces
in Afghanistan, the radical Mujahin,
which was being propped up by the US and
Pakistan as part of the cold war
rivalries.
USSR was eventually defeated, thrown out
of the country by the Mujai forces and
the Taliban was essentially a byproduct
of the Afghan Mujahiden and Taliban was
set up by the radical student leaders of
the Mujai. It was clearly a byproduct of
the Afghan mjai itself which had
defeated the USSR.
So now Russia which is focused on its
own interests has made its peace with
Taliban. It has been engaging with
Taliban from many years. Now it has
officially recognize the Taliban regime
as well. That's why it's a very very big
geopolitical development. Now this could
pave the way for China to give official
recognition as well and maybe other
countries could follow. That will create
a difficult question for India. Should
India also officially recognize the
Taliban regime or should we continue
with our balanced approach where we
maintain unofficial ties without the
diplomatic recognition? So what do you
think? Let me know in the comments. Now
coming to the prelim section, NPA
outbreak has been reported again in the
state of Kerala. This can be an
important topic for your prelims. Nepah
virus disease is caused by the npa virus
and it is essentially a zunotic illness
where the virus jumps from animals to
humans.
A zunotic jump is reported and it is
known to cause respiratory illness of
acute kind which could even lead to
encphilitis of the brain which could
become fatal. In fact, has a very high
fatality rate. The mortality rates are
pretty high and the transmission from
animals to humans primarily happens when
humans come in contact with those hosts
and reservoir animals and birds which
are considered to be the primary host
and reservoir of the Nepal virus. The
first ever outbreak of Nepal was in 1998
in Malaysia.
In fact, the disease itself is named
after this place in Malaysia called Nepa
where the first outbreak was reported.
So, it's a feature which is seen
primarily in tropical countries.
This outbreak spread to Singapore as
well and the primary source
was identified as contaminated pigs.
Pigs are considered to be the reservoirs
of the nippa and those who come in
contact with the fluids of these
infected animals, right? Farm workers,
uh those who work in slaughter houses,
those who consume the meat, they are at
greatest risk of exposure and
contracting the disease. And later
humanto human transmission is also
possible.
The other outbreak which is a very
different variant of the NPA was seen in
Bangladesh and India
in the late '9s and early 2000. So in
Indian states like West Bengal then as
well as in Kerala repeated outbreaks are
seen in Bangladesh as well such
outbreaks have been seen but in the case
of India and Bangladesh the the primary
cause is identified as the fruit bats
which are very common in the
subcontinent. they are reservoirs of the
nippai again. So coming in contact with
the excretion of the fruit bats or the
fruits that they have partially
consumed. Right? If humans were going to
eat those contaminated fruits,
especially fruits like berries or lii or
even dates or the syrup from the date
palm tree, that's when the highest
likelihood of contamination exists and
that's why outbreaks are predominantly
concentrated in Kerala and regions
around West Bengal. So as I said it
leads to
it's it leads to very serious symptoms
causing acute respiratory illness
leading to encphilitis and eventual
death. As of now there is no specific
treatment or drugs to cure the NPA
disease. Treatment provided is largely
symptomatic. Right? So symptomatic care
is given and there's no vaccine
available as well. The containment
strategy mainly revolves around limiting
the contact of humans with these
infected animals and reservoirs.
That is what you need to know about the
NIPA. Next, there's a detailed article
on page 7 regarding the manusur yatra
which has resumed. So let's understand
quickly about the importance of kailash
manasur yatra. The Mount Kailash and
Lake Manasarova
and as well as Lake Rashastal which are
located in Tibet they're considered to
be extremely sacred. It's part of a very
sacred pilgrimage across multiple
religions
not just Hinduism but even in Buddhism,
Janism and in several other faiths.
Mount Kailash has a lot of religious,
spiritual, cultural significance.
But given the fact that Mount Kyash and
Lake Manasar are in Tibet, which is
today under
Chinese sovereignty, ever since China
annexed Tibet in 1950, right? China has
full sovereignty over the region. The
access to these pilgrimage sites for
Indian pilgrims became restricted. But
the government of India has worked with
China
to enable the Kailash Manasar Yatra.
But in 2020, the Kailash Manasarov Yatra
came to a halt because of the COVID 19
restrictions that were brought in place.
Following this the India China military
standoff broke out
in Ladak
and as a result of these persistent
border tensions between India and China
until 2025
the manasuri yatatra was not resumed. So
for 5 years there was a gap in
organizing the kail manasar yatatra.
This is organized by the government of
India by the ministry of external
affairs
in collaboration with the government of
China, the PRC and the local
administration in Tibet.
Understood? So it's a government
organized pilgrimage and it's also seen
as part of our cultural ties with China.
China permits Indian pilgrims to access
Mount Kailash and Lake Manasar in a
pilgrimage that's organized by the
government of India in collaboration
with the Tibetan administration and as
well as the state governments of Sikkim
and Uttak. So you should be familiar
with the roots which are used by the
government of India to organize this
pilgrimage.
So after 5 years this pilgrimage is
resuming because just last year we
resolved the military standoff in Lada.
some normaly has come back to India
China relations and China and India have
restored the Kailash Manasar over Yatra.
So the first batch of pilgrims have been
chosen and they have already taken up
the pilgrimage. So one route which is
the most preferred and the easiest route
to access Mount Kailash is through the
Natula pass in Sikkim.
See Natula is a age-old historical link
between India and Tibet. Right? Buddhism
has traveled through this route.
Crossber trade has been taking place
since centuries through Natula. There
has been a lot of cultural exchange as
well and Natula also holds defense and
strategic significance today. So India
has been using the Natula route for
Kailash Manasur over Yatra. Though it is
a longer route as you can see there is a
motorable road that has been built in
Tibet by China which makes it easier to
access Mount Kailash. The trekking
involved is very less. So even senior
citizens
even those who are not physically very
fit
right can undertake this yatra through
the natula route which is facilitated by
the government of India with China and
the administrations of Tibet and uh
government of Sikkim.
Is that clear? Though it's a longer
route, it's much more easier because
almost till the end there's a motorable
road. Right? The trekking involved is
very less and minimal. The other route
which is actually a shorter route
is through the strategic Lipu lake pass.
Lipu lake is a strategic pass located at
the trijunction of India, Nepal and
China over here where Uttakan meets with
Tibet and Nepal near the Kalapani region
the disputed Kalapani region right which
is a dispute between India and Nepal.
That's where Lipo Lake pass is located.
Now this route though it is shorter it
is seen as more difficult because this
involves more trekking
and there was no motorable road till the
lipu lake route on the Indian side as
well the pilgrims had to trek a lot but
recently India has constructed a
strategic road linking Darula in
Uttakand
along the Nepal border directly with
Lipu lake so at least this stretch of
the route has become easier there's a
motorable all-weather road India has
built which has a strategic military uh
application as well but from Lipu lake
still there would be a lot of trekking
involved to reach and access mount
Kailash and lake Manasurover so this is
a slightly difficult route compared to
the Natula route and this is something
you should know about Kailash manasur
yatra coming to the last topic for today
under the economy section there's an
article referring to cartilization
and the role of competition commission
of India the CCI is investigating ating
allegations of cartilization by two
leading cement producers in our country.
Ultr tech cement and Dalmia cement.
Allegedly they have colluded together to
manipulate production and control prices
in order to maintain their dominance
over the market which is a
anti-competitive practice which
undermines competition. So what is
cartilization? Cartilization is where
two dominant players in a certain sector
or in with regard to a certain product
they collude. They come together to
secretly control the production, limit
the production deliberately to create
artificial demand and fix the prices so
they can continue to maintain their
monopoly or duopoly which is harmful to
the consumer interests. This could
stifle innovation. it could hurt
competition in the market and eventually
customers would be affected by such
cartilization.
So to act against these anti-competitive
practices to tackle cartilization and
other anti-competitive threats, India
has a statutory body which has been set
up the competition commission of India
which was established in the year 2003.
It is set up under the competition act
of 2002 and functions under the ministry
of corporate affairs and its primary
role is to protect the spirit of
competition in the Indian industry. So
it deals with illegal practices such as
cartilization.
It also regulates mergers and
acquisitions to prevent any hostile
takeovers.
It essentially tackles the rise of a
monopoly or even a duopoly
to ensure that the market market is
fragmented distributed. So there is
enough scope for competition to thrive
which will benefit the consumers. Only
when competition exists in the market
will quality of the product or service
be better. Only then the pricing would
be favorable to the consumer. So that is
the primary role of the competition
commission of India. Please make a note
of this and on this note I bring my
discussion to an end. I hope this
detailed analysis has been helpful and
please let me know what you think in the
comments and if you like the session do
press the like button. That is it for
today. See you tomorrow. Till then take
care. Have a good